Doug Fieger Papers ARC.0026
Library and Archives
Doug Fieger Papers
Bulk, 1979-1981
1978-2010, undated
ARC.0026
Library and Archives
7.83 Linear feet (2 records cartons, 1 Hollinger box, 1 oversize box, 1 shared flat file drawer)
The Doug Fieger Papers span the years 1978 to 2010, with the bulk of the papers dating between 1979 and 1981. The collection provides rich documentation of the power pop group, The Knack. The majority of the articles and clippings, audiovisual materials, business files, fan club documents, lyrics, and posters in the collection follow the career of the Knack from their smash hit in 1979, "My Sharona," to the revitalization of the song in 1994 in the film Reality Bites. The personal files and publications in the collection more accurately portray Fieger's interest in the lives of his family, friends, and colleagues, the role of Nick that he played on TV's Roseanne, and his love of vintage guitars. The collection highlights the life of a rock band from obscurity to superstardom and back again. It also provides perspective into Fieger's creative process, his career with and without the Knack, and his personal interests.
Fieger, Doug
Biographical Note
1952 August 20 Douglas Lars Fieger is born in Oak Park, Mich.
1964 February Fieger picks up the guitar and begins playing with John Coury.
1966 Fieger and Coury form the group Sky and are managed by the owner of the Grande Ballroom, Detroit.
circa 1968 Jimmy Miller signs Sky.
1970 Sky records their first album at Olympic Studios for RCA Records.
1971 Sky records their second album. Fieger meets Bruce Gary (Knack's first drummer).
1973 Feiger and Gary meet Berton Averre (lead guitar/backing vocals/keyboards for the Knack).
1974 Fieger plays bass for a short time in the German progressive rock band Triumvirat.
1978 June Meets last member of the Knack, Prescott Niles (bass), a week before the band's first show.
1979 Capitol Records wins bidding war for the Knack against 12 other record companies.
1979 August 25 "My Sharona," from the album Get the Knack, spends six weeks on Billboard's Hot 100.
1980 Album ...But the Little Girls Understand is released.
1981 Album Round Trip is released.
1982 The Knack breaks up.
1986-1987 The Knack regroups to tour.
1991 Billy Ward replaces Bruce Gary on drums. Don Was produces album Serious Fun for the Knack.
1994 Popularity of "My Sharona" is revived through use in the film Reality Bites.
1997 April Knack performs to capacity at the Viper Room.
1997 Knack performs on two tribute albums: Come and Get It: A Tribute to Badfinger and One Step Up/Two Steps Back: The Songs of Bruce Springsteen.
1998 Album Zoom is released on Rhino Records.
1999 Fieger releases solo album First Things First.
2001 Album Normal As The Next Guy is released. Laserdisc Live at the Rock 'n' Roll Funhouse is released.
2006 August 22 Bruce Gary dies of lymphoma.
2010 February 14 Fieger dies after battling cancer for many years.
Doug Fieger was best known as the lead singer of the Knack and co-writer with guitarist Berton Averre of the group's 1979 number one hit "My Sharona." His colorful and storied career went beyond that hit recording and the band, however, with an array of escapades in the music industry dating back to when he was a young teen with Jeff Beck, Bobby Keys, Jim Price, Pete Townsend, Traffic, and the Plastic Ono Band's Alan White, and a more serious side, including production work and interactions with Roy Orbison, Ringo Starr, and Was Not Was, among others.
Sources
"Doug Fieger." Wikipedia. Last modified 29 September 2010. Accessed October 8, 2010. http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Doug_Fieger.
"The Knack." Wikipedia. Last modified 5 October 2010. Accessed October 8, 2010. http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/The_Knack.
Viglione, Joe. "Doug Fieger." All Music Guide. Last modified 2010. Accessed October 8, 2010. http://allmusic.com/cg/amg.dll?p=amg&sql=11:fbfuxqr5ldfe~T1.
Schnee, Steve. "The Knack." All Music Guide. Last modified 2010. Accessed October 8, 2010. http://allmusic.com/cg/amg.dll?p=amg&sql=11:kifoxqe5ldse.
Access Restrictions
Collection is open for research. Patrons must sign the Acknowledgment of Legal Responsibility and Privacy Rights statement on the Researcher Registration form before using this collection. Consult the Library and Archives in advance of your visit to ensure access to these materials is available.
Separated Materials
45 rpm records, books, magazines, and concert programs in this collection have been transferred to the library. Please search for the "Doug Fieger Papers" in the library catalog for a list of donated titles. If you are unable to find what you are looking for, consult the Library and Archives staff to ensure these materials are available.
Custodial History note
The Doug Fieger Papers were received by the Rock and Roll Hall of Fame and Museum, Inc. as gifts from his sister Beth Falkenstein on September 3, 2010 and April 14, 2011.
Averre, Berton; Chapman, Mike; Falkenstein, Beth; Fieger, Doug; Gary, Bruce, 1952-2006; Knack (Musical group); Was (Not Was) (Musical group); Zappa, Frank; Business records; Clippings (Books, newspapers, etc.); Correspondence; Fan clubs; Files (Records); Legal instruments; New wave music--California; Newsletters; Popular music--United States; Posters; Rock groups--United States; Sheet music; Songs--Texts
- Series I: Articles, Clippings, and Photocopies, 1978-2010, undated
  Scope and Contents
  Series I: Articles, Clippings, and Photocopies pertains primarily to Fieger's work in The Knack and contains magazine and newspaper articles from all over the United States. The series is arranged chronologically by decade, except for those materials that had been previously compiled into smaller date spans by Beth Falkenstein or The Knack's management company.
  - Charts, 1979 (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Get the Knack magazine ad, 1979 (Box 4, Object 3)
  - Clippings and articles, 1978-1979 (Box 1, Folder 2-3)
  - Clippings and articles, 1980s (Box 1, Folder 4-5)
  - Knack, ...but the little girls understand ad from New Musical Express, 1980 March 15 (Drawer-folder FF.1.14-1, Object 13)
  - Knack, Round Trip ad from Billboard magazine, 1981 October 17 (Box 4, Object 5)
  - Clippings, 1981 (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - Clipping and articles, 1990s (Box 1, Folder 7-8)
  - Photocopied clippings, 1990-1991 (Box 1, Folder 9)
  - Knack, Serious Fun / "Rocket O' Love" newspaper ad, 1991 (Drawer-folder FF.1.14-1, Object 14)
  - Creem magazine front and back cover, 1994 May (Box 4, Object 1)
  - Reality Bites and Knack clippings, 1994 (Box 1, Folder 10)
  - Clippings and articles, 1998 (Box 1, Folder 11)
  - Clippings and articles, 2000s (Box 1, Folder 12)
  - Memorials to Fieger and Bruce Gary, 2006, 2010 (Box 1, Folder 13)
  - Clippings and articles, undated (Box 1, Folder 14)
  - Photocopy of photograph of Knack (Averre, Fieger, Ward, Niles) by Steve Granitz, undated (Box 4, Object 2)
- Series II: Business Files, 1977-2007, undated
  Series II: Business Files contains documents related to The Knack's album releases, promotions, and tours, as well as Doug Fieger's contracts and correspondence. The Series is broken down into six subseries: Albums, contracts, correspondence, miscellaneous, promotional materials, and tours and performances. The subseries are organized chronologically, with undated material at the end of each.
  - Subseries 1: Albums, 1979-2002, undated
    - Get the Knack, EMI Svenska AB recording form, 1979 (Box 1, Folder 15)
    - Record label copy: Round Trip, ...but the little girls understand, Get the Knack, 1980, undated (Box 1, Folder 16)
    - Knack compilation cassette, 1986 May (Box 1, Folder 17)
    - Fax re: commercial to use "My Sharona", 1988 September 14 (Box 1, Folder 18)
    - Serious Fun, Charisma Records documents, 1990-1991 (Box 1, Folder 19)
    - Capitol Retrospective liner notes, 1992, undated (Box 1, Folder 20)
    - Get the Knack - Liner and mastering notes, 2001-2002 (Box 1, Folder 21)
    - The Knack, Rock 'n' Roll Funhouse, 2001 (Box 1, Folder 22)
    - Capitol Records reissue handwritten notes, undated (Box 1, Folder 23)
    - Get the Knack reissue material, undated (Box 1, Folder 24)
    - Get the Knack DVD notes, undated (Box 1, Folder 25)
    - Handwritten liner notes by Michael Chapman, producer, undated (Box 1, Folder 26)
  - Subseries 2: Contracts, 1977-2001, undated
    - Demo recordings: Accounting and rejection letter from Elektra Asylum, 1977 (Box 2, Folder 1)
    - Letters of agreement and dissolution for The Knack and Scott Anderson, 1978-1981 (Box 2, Folder 2)
    - Notes, correspondence, and drafts re: Contract with Capitol Records, 1979 (Box 2, Folder 3)
    - Agreement with Ferris Ashley Productions (as solo artist), 1984 (Box 2, Folder 4)
    - Agreement with de Passe-Jones Management, 1984-1989 and undated (Box 2, Folder 5)
    - Agreements with Danny Sugarman Management and Miguel Cancel, 1984, 1987 (Box 2, Folder 6)
    - Agreement for representation with Bruce Gary and Pat Torpey, 1987 (Box 2, Folder 7)
    - Canada employment authorization, 2001 (Box 2, Folder 8)
    - Contract and script for Get the Knack album cover to appear on TV show, "Ed", 2001 (Box 2, Folder 9)
    - Contract notes, undated (Box 2, Folder 10)
  - Subseries 3: Correspondence, 1979-2001, undated
    - To Fieger from Paul Marks, ASCAP, 1979 September 17 (Box 2, Folder 11)
    - Fan letters, 1980-1998, undated (Box 2, Folder 12)
    - To Fieger from Bobby Roberts, 1981 May 29 (Box 2, Folder 13)
    - Sharona, 1982, undated (Box 2, Folder 14)
    - To Fieger from Ken Sharp, Denny Somach Productions, 1986 January 6 (Box 2, Folder 15)
    - To Fieger from Tony Clyburn (FOX 102), 1991 February 21 (Box 2, Folder 16)
    - Celebrity correspondence, 1991, 1993-1994, undated (Box 2, Folder 17)
    - Invitation to the 37th Annual Grammy Awards, 1995 (Box 2, Folder 18)
    - To Fieger from Berton Averre, 1996 November 7 (Box 2, Folder 19)
    - Letter from Dr. Herbert Rubin, re: Berton Averre's hand injury, 2001 November 27 (Box 2, Folder 20)
    - Letter from Mother, undated (Box 2, Folder 21)
    - To Fieger from Bruce Gary, Christmas (Box 2, Folder 22)
  - Subseries 4: Miscellaneous, 1979-2002, undated
    Subseries 4: Miscellaneous includes documentation from the National Academy of Songwriters, interviews, the 1994 release of Reality Bites, scripts from the television show Roseanne, a newsletter from Capitol Records, and more.
    - Capitol International Newsletter, 1979-1980 (Box 2, Folder 23)
    - Video file, 1981, undated (Box 2, Folder 24)
    - Odds and ends, 1990-1998, 2004, undated (Box 2, Folder 25)
    - "Hi! We're the Knack...", 1991 (Box 2, Folder 26)
    - "Roseanne" scripts for "Nick", 1992-1993 (Box 2, Folder 27-28)
    - Small Wonder (Fieger's post-Knack group), 1993 (Box 2, Folder 29)
    - Reality Bites and The Knack, 1994 (Box 2, Folder 30-31)
    - National Academy of Songwriters, 1994-1995 (Box 2, Folder 32)
    - Miscellaneous receipts, 1998-1999 (Box 2, Folder 33)
    - Requests for and drafts of interviews, 2000-2004 (Box 2, Folder 34)
    - Sit-N-Spin: Doug Fieger Top 12 Songs, 2002 June 11 (Box 2, Folder 35)
    - [List of possible band names before The Knack], undated (Box 2, Folder 36)
  - Subseries 5: Promotional Materials, 1979-2001, undated
    - The Knack press kit, 1979 Summer (Box 2, Folder 37)
    - Miscellaneous promotional and personal material, 1979-1981, undated (Box 2, Folder 38)
    - Promotional materials, 1979, 1998 (Box 2, Folder 39)
    - The Knack promotional material, circa 1979 (Box 2, Folder 40)
    - The Knack press kit (Italian/German), circa 1980 (Box 2, Folder 41)
    - Promotional material, circa 1980 (Box 2, Folder 42)
    - Press kit, 1994 (Box 2, Folder 43)
    - Cover of promotional CD for Zoom, 1998 (Box 2, Folder 44)
    - Promotional materials: Rock 'n' Roll Funhouse, Normal as the Next Guy, 2000-2001 (Box 2, Folder 45)
    - Artwork The Knack, undated (Box 2, Folder 46)
    - Promotional material, undated (Box 2, Folder 47)
    - The Knack stationery, undated (Box 2, Folder 48)
  - Subseries 6: Tours and Performances, 1978-2007, undated
    - Starwood guest list, 1978 (Box 2, Folder 49)
    - Show listings, 1978-2003, undated (Box 2, Folder 50)
    - The Knack Australian tour, August 1979 (Box 2, Folder 51)
    - The Knack European tour, 1979 (Box 2, Folder 52)
    - The Knack 1st world tour, America, 1979 (Box 2, Folder 53)
    - The Knack Phase II world tour, 1979 (Box 2, Folder 54)
    - Application to enter Japan on tour, 1979 (Box 2, Folder 55)
    - Tour itineraries and rehearsal schedules, 1979, 1981, 1990, undated (Box 2, Folder 56)
    - Tour itineraries, 1979, 1989, undated (Box 2, Folder 57)
    - The Knack "Around the World in '80" tour, 1980 (Box 2, Folder 58)
    - The Knack promotional tour, Italy, 1980 (Box 2, Folder 59)
    - Promotional tour itinerary, 1980 (Box 2, Folder 60)
    - Savoy program, 1981 Fall (Box 2, Folder 61)
    - Tour documents (contracts, itineraries), 1987 (Box 2, Folder 62)
    - The Knack on The Tonight Show with Jay Leno, 1994 (Box 2, Folder 63)
    - Viper Room, 1997 (Box 2, Folder 64)
    - Tour information, 1987, undated (Box 2, Folder 65)
    - Tour information, 2001-2004 (Box 2, Folder 66)
    - Contract to appear in Minnesota, 2004 April 10 (Box 2, Folder 67)
    - "Countdown Spectacular 2" tour, Australia, 2007 August-September (Box 2, Folder 68)
    - Set list, undated (Box 2, Folder 69)
- Series III: Fan Clubs, 1981, 1994, undated
  Series III: Fan Clubs contains newsletters and promotional advertisements for the Knack International Fan Club and the Knack Fan Club. The Series is chronological with undated material located at the end.
  - The Knack fan clubs newsletter ( Knack Knews), 1981, 1994 (Box 2, Folder 70)
  - Knack International Fan Club, undated (Box 2, Folder 71)
- Series IV: Lyrics, 1979-2003, undated
  Series IV: Lyrics contains handwritten and typed song lyrics and chord charts, as well as published sheet music for The Knack. Songs from the album Round Trip are featured prominently. Of note is a manuscript for the song "Don't Look Back," written by Bruce Springsteen. In 1979, The Knack recorded Bruce Springsteen's unreleased song, which remained an unissued studio track in the Capital vaults until the 1991 Retrospective. The track was later released again on the 1997 Capital Records' Springsteen tribute double CD Two Steps Forward, One Step Back. The Knack's "Don't Look Back" is the only released version of this Springsteen chestnut. In recording the song, the band increased the tempo and modified some of the lyrics. This series is organized chronologically undated material arranged alphabetically at the end.
  - Handwritten and published sheet music and lyrics, 1979-1980, undated (Box 3, Folder 1)
  - Typed lyrics for Round Trip album, 1981 (Box 3, Folder 2)
  - Nirvana's "Smells Like Teen Spirit" [handwritten by Fieger], 1994 (Box 3, Folder 3)
  - "My Daytona" lyrics, 2003 February-2003 March (Box 3, Folder 4)
  - "Don't Look Back" [written by Bruce Springsteen], undated (Box 3, Folder 5)
    General note
    These appear to a photocopy of the lyrics, handwritten by Bruce Springsteen in a spiral bound notebook.
  - Fieger's handwritten lyrics, undated (Box 3, Folder 6)
  - Handwritten lyrics for 3rd album, Round Trip, undated (Box 3, Folder 7)
  - Handwritten lyrics for "Frustrated", undated (Box 3, Folder 8)
  - Lyrics, undated (Box 3, Folder 9)
- Series V: Personal Files, 1979-2004
  Series V: Personal Files contains articles, clippings, and other publications related to some of Fieger's personal interests, family, and friends, including his brother Geoff's political career, Was Not Was, Aerosmith, the Rubber City Rebels, Frank Zappa, the Troubadour, and Charlie Bishop. The Series is arranged chronologically.
  - Personal interest file, 1979-2004 (Box 3, Folder 10)
  - Aerosmith's Get a Grip Tour, Glen Helen Blockbuster Pavilion, 1994 October 15 (Box 3, Folder 11)
- Series VI: Posters, 1979-2004
  Series VI: Posters includes promotional posters and a LP flat related to The Knack. The Series is arranged chronologically. Materials are stored out of sequence due to size and condition concerns.
  - Knack in concert, Utah State University, 1979 October 31 (Drawer-folder FF.1.14-1, Object 6)
  - Get the Knack, 1979 (Drawer-folder FF.1.14-1, Object 3)
  - "Get the Knack Get the Songbook", circa 1979 (Drawer-folder FF.1.14-1, Object 7)
  - "The Knack Get It", circa 1979 (Box 4, Object 13-14)
  - Knack, Capitol Records, 1980 (Drawer-folder FF.1.14-1, Object 4)
  - Knack, ...but the little girls understand and "La Nena Dice Tacos" b/w "Baby Talks Dirty", 1980 (Drawer-folder FF.1.14-1, Object 5)
  - Knack, Serious Fun, 1991 (Drawer-folder FF.1.14-1, Object 1)
  - Knack, Serious Fun flat, 1991 (Drawer-folder FF.1.14-1, Object 10)
  - Knack with special guests the Muffs, at Belly Up, 1994 May 2 (Box 4, Object 15-17)
  - Reality Bites, 1994 (Drawer-folder FF.1.14-1, Object 11)
  - Temecula Valley Balloon and Wine Festival: Knack; Motels; Spin Doctors; Fixx; Buck-O-Nine; Drew Davis Band, 2004 June 4-6 (Box 4, Object 6)
  - Knack at Golden Bear, January 18 (Box 4, Object 7)
  - Kingfish; Flora Purim; Knack; Zippers at Pacific Strand Theatre, February 17-March 10 (Box 4, Object 11)
  - Knack at Golden Bear, February 23 (Box 4, Object 8)
  - Knack, Entertainment 79 at the Catamaran Hotel & Restaurant, March 20 (Box 4, Object 12, Drawer-folder FF.1.14-1)
  - Knack, live in concert at the Roxy, April 28 (Drawer-folder FF.1.14-1, Object 8)
  - Knack at Royce Hall, UCLA, July 12 (Drawer-folder FF.1.14-1, Object 9)
  - "Mainstreet's August Groups": Ariel; Steel, Rick and the Hot Biscuit Band; Sheerlux; Phil Manning Band; Charisma; Knack, August 2-September 1 (Box 4, Object 4)
  - Knack at the Troubadour, September 22-24 (Box 4, Object 9-10)
  - Knack, Capitol Records/Toshbia EMI concert image, undated (Drawer-folder FF.1.14-1, Object 2)